<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="16"><page Index="1" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ CRISIL
Foundation
We Are More
Celebrating The First 5 Years
]]></page><page Index="2" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ CRISIL Foundation regards financial empowerment as
Increased awareness of available financial products and services, as well as social security schemes
Increased awareness of access points to such services
Creating demand for, and facilitating access to, relevant financial services
Sense of control over finances through control over savings and expenses
Confidence to make informed financial choices for self and family
Decisions related to household purchases, asset purchases.
Borrowing decisions (credit/loan)
Discerning between genuine and fraudulent investment products
The ability and discipline to set and achieve financial goals
By stronger financial capabilities, we mean
GLOSSARY
]]></page><page Index="3" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[     PROLOGUE
      At CRISIL, we are more than the work we do
for our clients.
As a responsible corporate citizen, we reach out to disadvantaged and excluded communities to strengthen their financial capabilities.
                                Mein Pragati,
our maiden
programme, for financial empowerment and inclusion, fuels the aspirations of marginalised families, for a better quality of life.
We believe that awareness, access and guidance, empower individuals.
         ]]></page><page Index="4" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ CRISIL Mitra
A trainer, someone who guides, mentors, and coaches villagers, the CRISIL Mitra (Mitra means friend) is often considered a local expert who empowers villagers in matters of household and personal finance.
The CRISIL Mitras help rural women monitor and optimise household cashflows. In doing so, they instill in the women the confidence to set financial goals, to make informed financial choices, and to transact independently.
MEET OUR FIELD FORCE
Sakhi
The Sakhi is an enterprising rural woman who has inculcated good financial habits as a direct outcome of Mein Pragati.
The torch bearer of our initiative, she helps villagers remain committed to achieving their financial goals. As someone who carries forward the CRISIL Mitra’s teachings, the Sakhi reiterates good financial practices through audio-messages; she also monitors progress and addresses the communities’ immediate financial needs.
]]></page><page Index="5" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 2015
On we go, to Assam
In 2015, we trained a team of 100 CRISIL Mitras to strengthen the financial capabilities of individuals and communities in rural Assam. Since then, CRISIL has been reaching out to communities in Barpeta, Darrang, Goalpara, Kamrup, Morigaon and Nalbari in Assam.
]]></page><page Index="6" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ Our CRISIL Mitras have also helped revive more than 500 Self-Help Groups (SHGs), making them functional once again. Many rural women in Assam approached CRISIL Mitras, expressing an intent to revive defunct SHGs.
CRISIL Mitras help such SHGs, guiding members with registration, book-keeping, and other administrative requirements. SHGs have also increased savings, with guidance from CRISIL Mitras. Consequently, SHGs begin saving systematically.
2015
]]></page><page Index="7" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 2016
Hello Rajasthan
Our geographic footprint extended to three districts in Rajasthan - Alwar, Dausa and Sikar, with 45 CRISIL Mitras. We were inspired to see our participants taking the onus to raise
financial awareness in their own families and neighbourhoods.
]]></page><page Index="8" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ STORIES OF CHANGE
Making resilience a way of life: Rashida Bibi
In a tragic turn of events, Rashida Bibi’s husband passed away in 2016. Our CRISIL Mitra, Moinuddin Ahmed, stood by the grieving family. He helped Rashida Bibi submit documents to file a claim for death benefit through the Pradhan Mantri Jeevan Jyoti Bima Yojana. Three months later, she received Rs. 2 lakhs in settlement.
Equipped with her new found knowledge through Mein Pragati, Rashida Bibi thoughtfully invested a portion of the settlement in her late husband’s cloth shop and a fixed deposit. She also leased a piece of land for cultivation, and deposited the remainder in her bank account. Rashida Bibi’s household income increased by 45%. She continues to look up to Moinuddin for financial advice.
]]></page><page Index="9" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ STORIES OF CHANGE
The path to self-sustenance : Manalisha SHG
The Manalisha Self-Help Group from Kamrup, Assam undertook strawberry farming in a greenhouse. However, the group discontinued operations, and disintegrated, after incurring losses. When the group met CRISIL Mitra, Rubul Das, during Mein Pragati interventions, he encouraged them to resume using the green house as a source of income.
With a renewed sense of confidence, the group began cultivating lady fingers and chillies in the green house. Armed with financial management skills, Manalisha’s members now profitably manage the greenhouse.
]]></page><page Index="10" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ STORIES OF CHANGE
Creating a ripple effect – Aarti Bhargava
“Before the launch of Mein Pragati, most of our villagers were unaware of any social security or Government-sponsored schemes providing insurance and health cover. You know how the situation is in remote villages. Had I availed of an insurance scheme before my husband’s accident, our savings would not have been used up”, rues Aarti. Not one to give in, and as a leader of a Self-Help Group, Aarti encouraged 14 members of
her group to invest in Jan Dhan and Bhamashah schemes.
“Women’s consent was hardly ever taken for financial decisions. With the help of CRISIL Mitras, that has changed now”, she smiles.
]]></page><page Index="11" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ STORIES OF CHANGE
Championing awareness – Meera Devi
“I am an Asha worker in Rajgarh, Alwar (Rajasthan). When I heard about Mein Pragati interventions in my community, I was keen to be a part of it.”
With her experience and network as a community health worker, Meera soon began championing financial awareness, leading to her selection as a
Sakhi for Mein Pragati. She now actively helps her fellow villagers complete documentation requirements for social security schemes and financial products/ services.
]]></page><page Index="12" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 2017
Into the hinterland
With a stamp of approval from India’s foremost banking regulator
The Reserve Bank of India invited CRISIL Foundation to set up MoneyWise Centers for Financial Literacy in Maharashtra and Haryana for a pilot.
We are the sole corporate-funded foundation empaneled by the RBI for its pilot to institutionalize support infrastructure for financial inclusion in villages. We have set up and will be managing 20 centres until 2020.
]]></page><page Index="13" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ STORIES OF CHANGE
“No one like you has approached us with such information.”
Vinod Gazri, Mangrulpir (Maharashtra)
“I like the programme, we all did. We learned about the Sukanya Samriddhi Yojana, insurance schemes (PMJDY, PMSBY) and the MUDRA scheme. I also learned that I could avail a loan. No one like you has approached us with such information. We will visit your centre to understand the facilities and financial schemes available to us. We have so far not been cheated and now with your guidance (on fraud prevention), we will not be
cheated in the future either.
Our villagers are not aware of anything that you shared today. Now that you are here, we want you to help us and the rest of the villagers, and make us aware (about financial schemes).”
]]></page><page Index="14" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ STORIES OF CHANGE
“The members have also started repaying loan installments to the bank.”
Ashubi, Malarka village (Haryana) (Tauru block in Mewat, now known as Nuh)
“Three of us set up a Self-Help Group (SHG) comprising 13 active members. The group has been operational for two years. We applied for an SHG loan. For about four months, we struggled to understand bank documentation and formalities. Then I happened to meet Poonam Devi - the Centre Manager of the Moneywise Centre for Financial Literacy, Tauru. I spoke to her about the trouble we were facing in understanding documentary
requirements and organising the paperwork. Poonam helped us comprehend bank formalities. She even accompanied us to the bank branch and helped with all formalities. With her support and guidance, our SHG received a loan. Our members have now invested in income-generating activities; some have set up a shop, or begun rearing a buffalo. The members have also started repaying loan installments to the bank.”
]]></page><page Index="15" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ 1,03,847
Women reached
86,300 Bank accounts opened
49,790 Loans 38,550 Insurance
policies
2015
25,763
5,351
5,804
6,564
2016
32,963
42,462
17,539
11,330
Alwar
OUR SOCIAL FOOTPRINT
2017
45,121
38,487
26,447
20,656
31,070
26,715
47,120
Assam
Darrang Morigaon
Rajasthan
2016
18,102
13,500
17,048
49,172
Ratnagiri
Maharashtra
2017
Haryana
2017
Villagers reached
Villagers reached
Sikar Dausa
Women reached
35,473 Bank accounts opened
64,075
Insurance Policies
Karnal Panipat
Gurugram
Mewat
MoneyWise Centres for Financial Literacy
Washim
22,472
21,596
Nalbari Kamrup
2017
Barpeta Goalpara
]]></page><page Index="16" isMAC="true"><![CDATA[ EPILOGUE
The Beginning of the Future
Mein Pragati is an initiative for change...
...A change in the way economically disadvantaged individuals think about money, manage money, and make financial decisions.
...A change in the way these individuals access financial services. ...A change in their way of living.
We will continue to be drivers for a positive wave of change, and by 2020, CRISIL Foundation will reach out to more than
1 million individuals across India.
]]></page></pages></Search>